Guide to the McNair Evans photographs, 2012-2013, 2017 RL.11557
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
McNair Evans photographs
2012-2013, 2017
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
RL.11557
6 Linear Feet 4 boxes 30 prints; 1 journal 24x29 inches
Shot during fifteen-day Amtrak train excursions, "In Search of Great Men" by photographer McNair Evans combines original photography with first-person, passenger-written accounts in an exploration of contemporary American culture and the people traveling on the Amtrak trains that criss-cross the United States. The photographic body of work consists of 30 large color digital prints, all sized 24x29 inches, featuring portraits of travelers and settings in train stations and passenger cars. The color prints are accompanied by a reproduction of a handmade photonarrative journal of 156 pages with 76 4x5 inch inkjet photographs, paired with comments and journal entries by the photographer, and reproductions of handwritten commentary by the passengers, who reflect on their lives and circumstances, including long-distance family relationships and problems with drug abuse. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Biographical Note
McNair Evans is a photographer based in San Francisco and a 2016 Guggenheim Photography Fellow.
He explores themes of shared experiences and identity by photographing the American cultural landscape admits forces of modernization. His personal, often autobiographical, subject matter is recognized for its literary character, unconventional narrative form, and metaphoric use of light.
Growing up in a small farming town in North Carolina, McNair Evans worked repairing track on a 32-mile railroad. He discovered photography studying anthropology at Davidson College, where he received a BA in 2001.
He continued his education with one-on-one mentorships with highly acclaimed pioneers of new documentary practices, Mike Smith of Johnson City, Tennessee, and Magnum Photographer Alec Soth, while earning a Masters of Fine Arts in Photography. Soth nominated McNair for the John Gutmann Foundation Photography Fellowship Award in 2014.
McNair's work has been exhibited across the country, and featured in editorial publications such as Harper's Magazine and The New Yorker, as well as on the cover of William Faulkner's novel, Flags in the Dust. He lectures regularly at universities and colleges.
He was the recipient of Duke University's 2017 Archive of Documentary Arts Award for Innovation in the Documentary Arts.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The McNair Evans photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2017.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Printed with Epson Stylus Pro 11880 on Moab Juniper Baryta Rag, 305 gsm, 100 percent cotton fiber paper with barium sulfate baryta surface, using Epson UltraChrome K3 ink.
The bound composition notebook journal in the collection includes inkjet prints and reproductions of handwritten texts.
Content Description
Shot during fifteen-day Amtrak train excursions, "In Search of Great Men" by photographer McNair Evans combines original photography with first-person, passenger-written accounts in an exploration of contemporary American culture through the people traveling on the Amtrak trains that criss-cross the United States. The photographic body of work consists of 30 large color digital prints, all sized approximately 24x29 inches, featuring portraits of travelers and settings in train stations and passenger cars. The color prints are accompanied by a reproduction of a handmade photonarrative journal of 156 pages with 76 4x5 inch inkjet photographs, paired with comments and journal entries by the photographer, and reproductions of handwritten commentary by the passengers, who reflect on their lives and circumstances, including long-distance family relationships and problems with drug abuse.
From the artist's statement: "Of course it can be a beautiful way to travel, but for the most part long-distance trains are for people trying to get their lives together, to find work, or to reunite with people they love whom they hope will love them back. This project explores that search for something just out of reach and a bit intangible. It is about the desire for change and the possibility of hope fulfilled...From the promotion of Manifest Destiny, to the creation of time zones, and the fraternal structure of the Civil Rights Movement, passenger train travel has shaped what it means to be American. Comparing this legacy to a prominent and evolving means of transportation in other nations, the current status of Amtrak and the relationships of passengers to the system at large is of great cross-cultural significance."
For this photographic project, McNair Evans received the 2017 Archive of Documentary Arts Award for Innovation in the Documentary Arts.
Separated Materials
Two photobooks with McNair Evan's work, Confessions for a Son, and Begin Anywhere, have been separated from the photograph collection and will be cataloged individually as part of the Rubenstein Library's holdings.
Documentary Photography -- United States; Drug abuse -- United States; Family -- United States; Passenger trains -- United States -- Photographs; Train travel -- Photographs; Travelers -- United States -- Personal narratives; Travelers -- United States -- Portraits; United States -- Economic conditions -- 1945-; United States -- Race relations; United States -- Social conditions -- 1980-; Color photographs; Inkjet prints; Journals; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Amtrak
- In Search of Great Men, 2012-2013, 2017
  - California Zephyr 32001, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.11557-P-0001)
  - Southwest Chief 15002, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.11557-P-0002)
  - Crescent 03001, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.11557-P-0003)
  - Crescent 13001, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.11557-P-0004)
  - Crescent 10001, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.11557-P-0005)
  - Crescent 01007, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.11557-P-0006)
  - Silver Star 23010, 2013 (Box 1, Image RL.11557-P-0007)
  - Sunset Limited 07005, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.11557-P-0008)
  - Carolinian 20010, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.11557-P-0009)
  - Capital Limited 12001, 2012 (Box 2, Image RL.11557-P-0010)
  - Capital Limited 13008, 2013 (Box 2, Image RL.11557-P-0011)
  - Capital Limited 07007, 2012 (Box 2, Image RL.11557-P-0012)
  - Capital Limited 01013, 2012 (Box 2, Image RL.11557-P-0013)
  - Southwest Chief 01009, 2012 (Box 2, Image RL.11557-P-0014)
  - California Zephyr 18005, 2012 (Box 2, Image RL.11557-P-0015)
  - Southwest Chief 27011, 2012 (Box 2, Image RL.11557-P-0016)
  - Crescent 11001, 2013 (Box 2, Image RL.11557-P-0017)
  - Empire Builder 06008, 2013 (Box 2, Image RL.11557-P-0018)
  - Lakeshore Limited 17001, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.11557-P-0019)
  - Southwest Chief 04003, 2012 (Box 3, Image RL.11557-P-0020)
  - Coast Starlight 03006, 2012 (Box 3, Image RL.11557-P-0021)
  - Sunset Limited 53007, 2012 (Box 3, Image RL.11557-P-0022)
  - Empire Builder 34010, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.11557-P-0023)
  - Crescent 29001, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.11557-P-0024)
  - California Zephyr 41005, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.11557-P-0025)
  - Silver Meteor 12002, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.11557-P-0026)
  - Empire Builder 22006, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.11557-P-0027)
  - Silver Star 02009, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.11557-P-0028)
  - Empire Builder 40009, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.11557-P-0029)
  - Empire Builder 31006, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.11557-P-0030)
  - Untitled bound composition book journal, 2017; 176 pages 1 volume (Box 4)